A Guide to the Bagby Family Papers, 1797-1900
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Bagby Family Papers, 1797-1900
Library of Virginia
24169
Negative Photostats, 136 prints (43 items).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Olive Bagby, Stevensville, Virginia, 22 June 1954
Biographical/Historical Information
John Bagby (1791-1880) was the son of Richard Bagby (1750-1818) and Susannah Jeffries Bagby (1765-1832). He was a large landowner and lived at "Bunker Hill" in King and Queen County. He operated a store in King and Queen County with his brother Richard Bagby. John Bagby married first Elizabeth Courtney (1792-1836) and they had eleven children, including Richard Hugh Bagby (1820-1870), John Robert Bagby (1826-1890), and Hannah Elizabeth Bagby (1822-1883). Hannah married John N. Gresham, who became a partner in his father-in-law's store. John Robert Bagby was the father of W. F. Bagby. John Bagby married second Elizabeth Lumpkin Motley (1799-1880) and they had three children.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1797-1900, of the Bagby family of King and Queen County, Virginia, consisting of agreements, bonds, deeds, field notes, notices, plats, promissory notes, suit papers, surveys, and wills. Deeds are for property in King and Queen County, and Middlesex County, Virginia, and for slaves. Wills are from King and Queen County, and Essex County, Virginia. Surveys and plats are for properties in King and Queen County or unspecified counties. Notices concern the inheritance of an estate, purchase of corn, appointment of commissioners for bridge repair, and payment of monies owed to S. P. Insurance Company. Elizabeth Bagby, John Bagby, John R. Bagby, Robert B. Bagby, Richard Bagby, Richard H. Bagby, Travis Bagby, and W. F. Bagby are the family members mentioned in the documents.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Notice, n.d., 2 prints.; Children of Theo. and Maria Baughan state that they are agreeable to Elijah Baughan being given by his mother at her death the homestead and ten adjoining acres in return for the support and care of the mother while she lives. Signed by eight children. (Folder 1)
- Field notes, n.d., 2 prints.; Survey of that part of Duval's Tract lying on the east side of the road. County not cited. Copy. (Folder 1)
- Plat, n.d., 1 print.; Unidentified plat of 17 acres and 51-1/4 acres. County not cited. (Folder 1)
- Deed, 1 September 1797, 2 prints.; John M. Stevens, City of Richmond, to James Bray, King and Queen County, 50 acres in King and Queen County. Recorded in King and Queen County, 11 December 1797. (Folder 1)
- Deed, 20 February 1800, 4 prints.; Thomas Stevens, Augusta County, to James Bray, King and Queen County, 50 acres in King and Queen County. Recorded 14 July 1800. (Folder 1)
- Deed, 4 May 1802, 2 prints.; Mary Dudley, King and Queen County, to daughter Milley Dudley, a slave named Patience. (Folder 1)
- Will, 18 April 1809, 3 prints.; Richard Richards, Essex County. Probate date is not included. Copy. (Folder 1)
- Bond, 24 April 1811, 2 prints.; John Bray to John Redd. (Folder 1)
- Survey, 16 October 1813, 2 prints.; Of 55-1/4 acres in King and Queen County belonging to John Redd, deceased, by Larkin Deshazo, surveyor. (Folder 1)
- Deed, 24 January 1814, 3 prints.; John G. Meredith, King and Queen County, to Robert Courtney and John Bagby, Jr., a negro named Lucy and her daughter Fann. (Folder 1)
- Deed, 1 December 1813, 6 prints.; Lewis Howerton and wife, Elizabeth, to James Webb, Essex County, 290-1/2 acres in King and Queen County. Recorded King and Queen County, 14 March 1814. (Folder 1)
- Suit papers, 1803-1817, 4 prints.; Executors of John Carlton vs. Robert Smith, Jr., and John Williams, King and Queen County. Copy. (Folder 1)
- Bond, 22 February 1819, 2 prints.; John Bagby, Jr. and John S. Stubbs to Ambrose Smith. (Folder 1)
- Deed, 15 May 1822, 4 prints.; Philip T. Montague, Middlesex County, to John Bagby, King and Queen County, and John Williams, King and Queen County, 145 acres in Middlesex County. Recorded Middlesex County, 23 September 1822. (Folder 1)
- Will, 12 July 1823, 3 prints.; Richard Gresham, King and Queen County. Recorded King and Queen County, 10 November 1823. (Folder 1)
- Bond, 18 May 1825, 2 prints.; Richeson Eubank and C. A. Hodges to John Bagby. (Folder 1)
- Plat, 13 October 1825, 2 prints.; 14 acres belonging to John Red, by Temple Walker, surveyor. County not cited. (Folder 1)
- Notice, 16 September 1825, 2 prints.; Robert B. Bagby, as agent for John Bagby and Richard Bagby, purchases corn of William Gregory of King William County. Included is a receipt for money received by Roger Gregory for William Gregory, 18 October 1825. (Folder 1)
- Bond, 22 October 1825, 2 prints.; John Bagby and Ro. Courtney to John Deshazo. Included is assignment from John Deshazo to Phil B. Pendleton, 26 October 1825. (Folder 1)
- Bond, 9 January 1826, 2 prints.; John Bagby and Richard Bagby to Alexander Fleet. (Folder 1)
- Plat, 15 January 1826, 2 prints.; 17-1/2 acres belonging to William Jeffries, by Temple Walker, surveyor. County not cited. (Folder 1)
- Plat, 7 June 1826, 2 prints.; 14-3/4 acres belonging to John Bagby, by Vincent F. Cauthorn. County not cited. (Folder 1)
- Deed, 24 December 1825, 4 prints.; Mary Shepherd, Leroy Shepherd, Mary Shepherd, Jr., William Wayne, and wife Nancy, to John Redd, both parties of King and Queen County, three-fourths of 14 acres in King and Queen County. Recorded King and Queen County, 12 June 1826. (Folder 1)
- Bond, 13 January 1827, 3 prints.; John Redd, Richard Bagby, Robert B. Bagby, John C. Richards, Richard H. Harwood, John R. Haynes, and Travis Bagby to John Bagby. (Folder 1)
- Agreement, 22 July 1829, 2 prints.; William Wyatt to act as overseer for John Bagby. (Folder 1)
- Plat, 15 and 22 June 1839, 2 prints.; 648 acres belonging to John Bagby in King and Queen County, by James G. White, surveyor. (Folder 1)
- Will, 20 February 1846, 2 prints.; Elizabeth Bagby. County and probate date are not included. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 13 January 1848, 4 prints.; Robert S. Pendleton, and wife Elizabeth, to Benoni Carlton, both parties of King and Queen County, personal and real estate. Acknowledged in King and Queen County, 13 January 1848. Acknowledged also before P. V. Daniel, Commissioner of Deeds for the state of Mississippi, City of Richmond, Virginia, 24 February 1848. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 20 July 1850, 4 prints.; John Bagby to Richard H. Bagby, both parties of King and Queen County, 300 acres in King and Queen County. Recorded in King and Queen County, 11 October 1852. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 20 March 1852, 4 prints.; James C. Roy, and wife Mary E. Roy, to Richard H. Bagby, both parties of King and Queen County, 5 acres, 11 poles in King and Queen County. Recorded King and Queen County, 11 October 1852. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 12 February 1853, 5 prints.; Dr. John DuVal, and wife Mildred R. DuVal, to Richard H. Bagby, both parties of King and Queen County, two acres in King and Queen County. Recorded King and Queen County, 14 February 1853. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 14 March 1853, 4 prints.; Franklin Courtney, and wife Adeline, of state of Louisiana, William P. Courtney, and wife Martha E. Courtney, of King and Queen County, Virginia, to John Ro. Bagby and John N. Gresham of King and Queen County, 11-1/4 acres in King and Queen County. Recorded in King and Queen County, 28 April 1853. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 14 April 1854, 4 prints.; John N. Gresham, and wife Hannah E. Gresham, to John R. Bagby, both parties of King and Queen County, their interest in 11-1/4 acres in King and Queen County. Recorded King and Queen County, 3 June 1854. (Folder 2)
- Will, 16 August 1855, 8 prints.; John Bagby, King and Queen County. Probate date is not included. (Folder 2)
- Promissory note, 15 November 1855, 2 prints.; R. H. Bagby and John Ro. Bagby to John N. Gresham. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 8 February 1858, 4 prints.; John N. Gresham, and wife Hannah E. Gresham, to John Ro. Bagby and Richard H. Bagby, both parties of King and Queen County, 378 acres [in King and Queen County]. Recorded King and Queen County, 8 February 1858. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 30 March 1858, 2 prints.; William F. Gardner to John Bagby, King and Queen County, interest due from John W. Faulconer for purchase of land. (Folder 2)
- Notice, 4 August 1859, 2 prints.; John D. Bagby, Marius P. Todd, and Phileman Bird appointed commissioners to receive proposals for repairing or rebuilding two bridges, King and Queen County. (Folder 2)
- Will, December 1860, 7 prints.; John Bagby, King and Queen County. Probate date is not included. (Folder 2)
- Notice, 2 March 1861, 1 print.; All monies due S. P. Insurance Co. to be paid to or transmitted to the treasurer, by William Wright, secretary. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 9 September 1869, 8 prints.; William Dow, trustee for Columbia Gresham and children, to Gresham and Bagby, John Ro. Bagby, William B. Bird, and John N. Gresham, 99 acres. Recorded King and Queen County, 18 November 1869. (Folder 2)
- Deed, 29 August 1873, 4 prints.; John Bagby to John R. Bagby, trustee, personal property. Recorded King and Queen County, 30 August 1873. (Folder 2)
- Survey, 7 April 1900, 4 prints.; 179 acres belonging to W. F. Bagby, by Francis W. Smith, surveyor. (Folder 2)